I use AI agents for research a lot.
They search, read, filter, and summarize 1000s
of documents for me in just minutes.
But this introduces a new problem.
You see, it's now too easy for research to end up with piles
and piles of documents, just like how developers are
drowning in code review work.
So, here's what I do instead.
This command here imports just 10 articles, and
autonomously builds a set of summaries or personal
Wiki pages.
And if I import, say, let's say, 90 more.
This will take a little bit longer.
It handles the larger size just fine, and the number
of wiki pages has only gone from five from our 10 sources
to 23 from our 100 sources.
Meanwhile, the original knowledge is still available to me
and the agents.
In other words, the human readable wiki remains manageable,
while the AI index preserves detailed source
linked knowledge.
How do I build this?
Well, I did it by expanding the LLM Wiki concept
with elastic searches AI index at its core.
Now, an AI index is designed to store knowledge efficiently
for AI agents, which makes it a natural fit for this project.
So, let me show you how that works and take you through
the journey of how I got there.
Here's the basic architecture.
The top part here shows what I call the machine memory layer.
It starts with the raw sources, so articles, documents,
or whatever I'm researching.
When I ingest a sauce, an LLM automatically turns
it into a set of knowledge indicators or KIs, which
are then stored in the elastic search AR index.
Achaia is just one useful piece of knowledge, and
crucially, it keeps the URL of the source it
came from, so every result stays traceable
back to the full source.
This is the small but important magic that allows detailed
memory to keep growing.
And that machine memory, in turn, powers 2 separate paths,
the read only queries CLI retrieves KIs,
and their source URLs directly.
It doesn't change the wiki.
Now, the maintainer LLM is different.
It receives the new KIs retrieves relevant
history from the AI index and reads the existing wiki context.
Then, it updates only the pages that need to change.
The result is a compact wiki index and a set of topic
pages that I can use as a starting point for my learning.
And I can tell you, from having used LLM wikis
for a little while, that they make it so much easier for my small
brain to process and digest information.
Now, this is the final outcome, but it's not necessarily
where I started, so let me show you why and how I
made those decisions.
My starting point was the LLM wiki.
This is an idea floated by Andre Capati.
That's right, that Andre Capati.
His thesis was that rag is useful, but LLM
is rediscovering knowledge from scratch on every question and
that there's no accumulation.
So, he proposed that instead of just retrieving
from raw documents at query time, the LLM
incrementally builds and maintains a persistent wiki.
One where you're in charge of sourcing, exploration,
and asking the right questions, so the LLM does all the grunt work.
Like many of these ideas, it's a deceptively simple,
but a super observant one that comes from a deep understanding
and intuition.
He proposes to let the LLMs do what they're good at, which is
reading and manipulating big volumes of information.
While you curate the direction of the wikis.
So you can probably see why this is a great idea with
lots of adoption in forms of packages, websites, extensions, and so on.
But this, let's call it vanilla, LLM
wicki, has a few limitations around scaling
and efficiency.
So let me explain what I mean by that.
The idea of asking an LLM to produce summaries,
you know, wiki sounds simple enough, right?
A new source comes in, it gets sent to an LLM,
and it makes updates the wiki articles.
easy, right?
Well, it turns out there are 2 problems with this, and
both of them kind of get worse over time.
And they relate to context.
The 1st problem is that comparing a source article to a bunch
of summaries is just a difficult task.
So imagine that you've never seen or read the Lord of the Rings.
And someone gives you a book synopsis, like Frodo
and his friends have to journey to Mordo to destroy a magic ring and
prevent it from falling to the wrong hands.
And then they give you the full scene of Gandalf confronting ceremony
at Isengard and ask you whether this should be in the summary.
Well, how could you possibly know?
You just can't.
You just don't have enough apples to Apple's context in your brain.
At that point, you either have to make a total guess, which congratulations,
you've learned to be like an LLM, or you have to now go back and
read the Lord of the Rings.
Which brings us to the 2nd problem, the context window,
in order for the LLM to make an apples to Apple's comparison and
evaluation of these sources, it must rate all
of the relevant information, which, in the case of vanilla
LLM wikis, means reading source materials.
Now, and the growing number of them, too, as the
wiki grows over time.
This is slow and wasteful.
It'll cost you growing amounts of time and LLM inference costs.
So, that's how I arrived at the solution that leverages
elastics AI index and knowledge indicators.
On AI index is an elastic search index designed
to save agents from repeatedly and inefficiently
looking for information.
Instead of an agent looking for files, performing searches or
running commands, all of which will cost you toykens and money,
an AI index will do all of that upfront.
So you do it once, store the outputs, and make that
knowledge searchable for later.
The things that indexes can be thought of as small morsels or nuggets
of knowledge, which is why they're called knowledge indicators.
In this repo, I simply send the source to an LLM
with a set of instructions, which will in turn output a set of KIs.
Then instead of this source, I get a set of useful
claims, explanations, or relationships, each with
a link back to the source.
Those KIs then get added to our AI index, which
of course is searchable.
As it turns out, AI index is a great solution for
our context problem.
So instead of making our maintainer LLM, choose between
using lossy summaries, always full-long documents,
we fill this AI index with compact, easy to search KIs.
Now, the maintainer LLM's workflow is different.
When a new source document is to be added, a pipeline
turns that into a set of KIs to be added to the AI index.
And then, the maintainer looks through the existing wiki pages
to see where and if those KIs might fit in.
And when it does find those relevant pages, it can selectively
retrieve other KIs from the AI index to compare
the full context, but in a much more efficient and
apples to Apple's way.
In other words, it looks at new KIs, historical
KIs, and the wiki pages that might need to change.
This is far more efficient than feeding a stack of full documents
to your LLM.
and it's far more complete than feeding the wikis and the new document.
So hopefully all of this sounds pretty straightforward.
Convert sources into KIs up front, and then use LLMs
to manage the final Wiki's profit.
But let me tell you about a pretty important failure mode that I came across.
My 1st attempt at running this app turned 25
blogs into just 23 wiki pages.
In other words, I've built this complex system so that I have
to look at an 8% reduction in the document count.
So that's not so great, right?
So if you imagine if the official Wikipedia has 92%
of the page count of all of the internet.
It's not really going to be ideal.
So, what helped here for me was to steer the LLM.
The key phrase to add for me was detailed or narrow
KIs may remain available only through the AI index.
This led the LLM note to focus the output on human readable
summary documents.
And with this change prompt, the next run produced
only 14 documents down from 23.
And the nice thing was that as I ingested more and more
data, the better we could see the benefit of the structure.
So let me show you how that worked.
What I have here is a wiki of recent elastic search labs,
blogs, generated from ingesting 100 blog entries.
But not all at once.
You see, the thing is, I want to simulate how a real wiki would
grow over time.
And really, you wouldn't be ingesting 100 articles at once
and summarizing it.
You know, you're not writing a graduate thesis over here.
Instead, I broke it up into batches of three files to simulate
an incremental growth in knowledge.
And that captured how some files grow over that time,
like this page on vector search benchmarking.
So this file was actually created on the first batch of documents
that were ingested, and capture some pretty good overall tips
on how to do benchmarking.
And then, as more documents get ingested, this wiki
page grows in length while remaining pretty reasonable overall.
So by the time all 100 blog entries are added, the page
collates information from 16 different sources.
It not only has these high-level tips about benchmarking,
but also a lot of detailed nuggets about how specific features
might affect benchmarks and how certain features might
improve performance in certain situations.
Looking at the bigger picture, we see that the number of wiki
pages grew like this.
You see that it maintains some sort of log ish scale
as we ingest more sources, which is key to
keeping our human facing wicket maintainable, even
as the sources keep growing.
So in the meantime, if we take a look at the raw data, you
see the KIs rise more or less in proportion with the document
count, meaning that all the raw data is available
for you and your agent as you need.
Let me show you the core function in my code base.
It loads the new KIs and wiki manifest established overall tasks.
The 1st LLM call chooses the page bodies and
historical searches that it needs.
This helps the model find the right context to review.
And then this 2nd LLM call returns the local page operations.
So what pages to update or create, and what changes
to make concretely.
And lastly, the wiki validates those changes and
checkpoints the sources.
This combines LLM calls with deterministic workflows,
the LLM returns structure data, and our program
implements the changes in a predictable way.
I've shared the code base, including the runnable example, prompts
validation, and so on in the repo here.
So if you want to see what an implementation of an LLM
wiki with the elastic search AI index looks like,
please check it out, and you can use it with a free trial of
elastic search as well, which is very nice.
This current version is to work with a particular adjacent shape,
but of course, you can adapt it to whatever data source and
shape that works for you.
And similarly, it's built with typescript, but obviously it can adapt
it to any language.
Elastic search client libraries are available in 8 different languages,
and you can use it with direct rest calls, of course.
And for agentic work, you can use the elastic agent skills,
or even try the new elastic CLI, which, as of now,
is in technical preview, but by the time you watch it, maybe it won't be.
should go and check it out.
Look, AI agents make collecting research ridiculously
easy, but they also create giant piles of documents
that will just sit on my desktop until deletion, basically.
So, a mark done-based LLM managed
wiki is a really good solution to all of this.
It gives me a high level overview without draining me in information.
And by integrating the elastic AI index as
the back end for all this, I was able to make the LLM
wiki sustainable, to manage as it scales up.
And hopefully also consistent in how it treats
the mix of all the information and new information.
And this pattern for me was relatively easy to understand and robust.
And what's also nice about it is that it's not just limited
to wikis, AI indexes could support any kind
of big and deep knowledge bases, cutting down on retrieved
context, and giving agents solid bases to work off of.
So I think there's high utility for all sorts of things for
AI indexes, technical documentation, internal
knowledge bases, or really anywhere that an agent keeps rediscovering context.
So, if you want to try my version, I've shared the typescript
repository in the description, and I also link to elastic search
server list and elastic searches back to database project,
which you should check out as well.
Now, I'm sure I'm going to come across new problems as I keep
using the LLM Wiki.
So I'd love to know how you would decide when a growing
wiki topic should be split, or what other failure modes
you think I'm about to discover the hard way.
Let me know in the comments, and thanks for watching and I'll see you next time.